A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Papers of the Study for the Ford Foundation on Policy and Program (Gaither Commission) FA709
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Papers of the Study for the Ford Foundation on Policy and Program (Gaither Commission)
1947-1956
bulk
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA709
2.64 Cubic Feet
Sketch of the Committee
"In the Fall of 1948, anticipating final settlement of Federal Estate Tax matters and the probable receipt during 1949 and 1950 of income sufficient to permit the Foundation to undertake a greatly expanded program, a Study Committee was appointed to act as independent consultants to the Foundation. This committee was made up of men widely known and respected in such fields as education, public health, the natural sciences, political science, the social sciences, the humanities, and modern business and industry. Members of the study Committee were Mr. H. Rowan Gaither Jr., Chairman; Thomas H. Carroll, D.C.S.; Charles C. Lauritsen, Ph.D; William C. DeVane, Ph.D; Donald G. Marquis, Ph.D; T. Duckett Jones, M.D.; Peter H. Odegard, Ph.D; Francis T. Spaulding, Ed.D. A Staff directed by Mr. Gaither served the Committee and included Mr. William McPeak and Mr. Dyke Brown, Assistant Directors; Mr. Paul Bixler; and Mr. Don K. Price." ..."The Study Committee agreed at the outset that the purpose of the study was not to accumulate a comprehensive catalogue of projects which the Foundation might undertake, but to block out in general terms those critical areas where problems were most serious and where the Foundation might make the most significant contributions to human welfare." (from Report to the Trustees, October 1950, pp. 3-4, 5)
"The work of the Study Committee was concluded in November 1949, when its General Report containing the Committee's conclusions and recommendations was submitted to the Trustees. ... Publication of the Report was authorized by special action of the Trustees on September 6, 1950." (from the preface of the General Report, p. 11)
Scope and Contents
This collection is made up of two series: Series I contains the working papers of the Study for the Ford Foundation on Policy and Program, and Series II consists of drafts and summaries of the Committee's Report as well as some Report-related material.
"The Report of the study for the Ford Foundatlon on Policy and Program" was published in September 1950. This report proposed five program areas to be the focal points of the Ford Foundation's operations. The published report was comprised of four volumes: volume I, the General Report; volumes II and III, Committee and Division Reports; and volume IV, Staff Memoranda.
The material in these papers covers the years 1947 (1948-1950) to 1956 and consists of six boxes of notes, intercommittee memoranda, correspondence, proposals, reports, summaries and drafts. Minutes of several Ford Foundation Trustee meetings are also included in the papers. While the collection contains many documents that are duplicated in the final report, it also includes original material that chronicles the methods of the study, the development, and the publicatlon of the Committee's Report. It also contains some material which pertains to the policy and program decisions published in the Report.
In conclusion, these papers provide a background for the Committee's Report, but do not stand as a substitute. For a complete accounting of the workings and findings of the Committee, the researcher should address himself to the four volumes of the "Report of Study for the Ford Foundation on Policy and Program."
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in two series:
I. The Working Papers for the Study for the Ford Foundation on Policy and Program, 1947-1956
II. Drafts and Summaries of the Study for the Ford Foundation on Policy and Program, 1949-1951
Conditions Governing Access
Material more than ten years old is open for scholarly research.
Select individual files are restricted, as noted. Permission to access these files must be obtained from the Ford Foundation before scholarly access is permitted.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be restricted from scholarly research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment.
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be restricted from scholarly research at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/RAC Head of Reference.
Ford Foundation
- The Working Papers for the Study for the Ford Foundation on Policy and Program, 1947-1956; I
  Scope and Contents
  The papers in Series I document the overall operation of the Committee and the fundamental decisions that were made by its members regarding the formulation of program disciplines, trustee selection, and the coordination and executlon of the study itself. The modus operandi of the group was to solicit suggestions from people not formally connected to the Study. The papers include correspondence among Committee members and individuals outside the committee. This correspondence demonstrates the wealth of ideas regarding policy and program that were submmitted to the Committee for consideration. Included among the correspondence are numerous proposals, sollcited and unsolicited, suggesting policy and program areas. Also included in this series are skeletal reports, drafted midway through the study, by the following Committee members: Thomas H. Carroll, Charles C. Lauritsen, Donald G. Marquis, T. Duckett Jones and Peter H. Odegard.
  With respect to the functioning of the Ford Foundation, the papers address two issues: the tax status of a philanthropic institution, and a code of by-laws for the administration of such an establishment.
  Arrangement
  Series I consists of 2 linear feet of material. The folders had no obvious arrangement scheme to begin with, and so they were regrouped into clusters of similar topics or materials: inter-committee memoranda, correspondence and proposals among committee and non-committee members, the development of the Study Committee Report, skeletal reports by Committee members, the Foundation's tax status and by-laws, and trustee materials. Within each folder the material ls arranged chronologically. However, the correspondence and proposals among committee and non-committee members are arranged alphabetlcally within each folder. It should be noted that in the latter material, for the year 1948, there is no H - R correspondence. Also, all items marked "miscellaneous - no author" were filed in the beginning of the "A" folder.
  - Staff Committee Memoranda, 1948 December - 1949 May (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Informational Memoranda, 1949 January - March (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Informational Memoranda, 1949 March - April (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Informational Memoranda, 1949 April - June (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Study Report Correspondence and Proposals A - B, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Study Report Correspondence and Proposals C - G, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Study Report Correspondence and Proposals [H] S - W [Z], 1948 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Study Report Correspondence and Proposals A - B, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Study Report Correspondence and Proposals C, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Study Report Correspondence and Proposals D - I, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Study Report Correspondence and Proposals J - L, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Study Report Correspondence and Proposals Mc - N, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Study Report Correspondence and Proposals [O] P - S, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Study Report Correspondence and Proposals T - W [Z], 1949 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Study Report Correspondence and Proposals A - C, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Study Report Correspondence and Proposals D - L, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Study Report Correspondence and Proposals Mac - MZ, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Study Report Correspondence and Proposals N - W [Z], 1950 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Activity Reports (Also includes correspondence and memoranda), 1948 October - 1949 February (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Activity Reports (Also includes correspondence and memoranda), 1949 February - 1950 September (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Background of the Administration of the study: Summaries of suggestions received from persons interviewed (1 of 2), 1949 January - May (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Background of the Administration of the study: Summaries of suggestions received from persons interviewed (2 of 2), 1949 January - May (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Background on the Administration of the Study - Correspondence, [1948-1949?] - 1950 February (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Planning, 1948 - 1949 May (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Human Welfare and Relative Importance of Problems and Programs, [1948-1949?] - 1950 January (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Suggested Program Area: Social (Human) Relations, [1949?] (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Tentative Statement of Suggested Program Areas for Ford Foundation Support, [1949?] (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Skeletal Report, by Carrol, Thomas H., 1949 March (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Outline Suggested by T. Duckett Jones for Consideration, 1949 March (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Preliminary Form of a Proposed Statement from the Health Division submitted by T. Duckett Jones, 1949 May (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Suggestions for a Statement Concerning Ford Foundation Policies by T. Duckett Jones, 1949 September (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Skeletal Report Natural Science Division, by Lauritsen, Charles C., 1949 March (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Tentative Statement submitted by P. H. Odegard, 1949 March (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Memorandum on Conferences and Interviews for the Study for the Ford Foundation, 1949 April (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Aims and Objectives of the Ford Foundation [Notes on March 1949 Meeting], Marquis, D. G., 1949 April (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Publishing Report, 1948 November - 1950 June (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Publishing Report, 1950 June - November (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Public Relations, 1947 April - 1950 December (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Income Tax Exemption, 1948 November - 1949 November (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Income Tax Exemption, 1950 October - 1956 January (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Income Tax Exemption, 1950 October - 1956 January (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Proposed Bylaws of the Foundation, [1948-1949?] - 1949 December (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Proposed Bylaws of the Foundation, 1950 January - [April] (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Proposed Bylaws of the Foundation, 1950 April - February (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Trustee Meetings and Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1945 December - 1949 November (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Trustee Meetings and Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1950 February - 1951 January (Box 4, Folder 46)
- Drafts and Summaries of the Study for the Ford Foundation on Policy and Program, 1949-1951; II
  The material in Series II represents the study's final phases, and the period immediately following the publication of the Report. Included in Series II is a report entitled, "Summary of the Committee's Recommendations and Conclusions." This document provides an overview of the Committee's work and contains excerpts from certain sections of the flnal four-volume report. This series also contalns a set of inter-office memoranda together with excerpts of staff reports to the Foundation's Trustees. This compilation of material, filed as a slngle document, examines the Foundation's execution of the Study Committee's final recommendations on policy and planning.
  Series II consists of .75 linear feet of material. The documents are arranged chronologically.
  - Foundation Trustees, 1948 November - 1949 August (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Draft of the General Report, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Report of the study for the Ford Foundation on Policy and Program, General Report, preliminary printing, 1949 October (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Report of the study for the Ford Foundation on Policy and Program, General Report, preliminary printing [annotated], 1949 October (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Summary of Study Recommendations and Conclusions and Agenda for Conference with Trustees (Copy 1), 1950 January (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Summary of Study Recommendations and Conclusions and Agenda for Conference with Trustees (Copy 2), 1950 January (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Excerpts from "Summary of Study Recommendations and Conclusions", 1950 January (Box 6, Folder 53)
  - Term of Existence of the Ford Foundation, 1950 February (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - Maximizing Effectiveness of Foundation Grants, 1950 March (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - Analysis of Program and Grant Application, 1950 April (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - [Interoffice Memoranda and Reports to the Board of Trustees re "Report to the Study for the Ford Foundation on Policy and Program"], 1949 November - 1950 October (Box 6, Folder 57)
- Appendix A
  Appendix A
  The following is the table of contents for the four volumes of the "Report of the Study for the Ford Foundation on Policy and Planning":
  VOLUME I Report of the Study for the Ford Foundation on Policy and Program
  VOLUME II Committee and Division Reports Report of Business Division Report of Health Division Policy of Deferred Attention to Certain Health Problems Report of Humanities Division Report of Natural Science Division Report of Education Division
  VOLUME III Committee and Division Reports (Continued) Report of Political Science Division Report of Social Science Division Proposed Policy for Private Institutions of Higher Education Conservation of Resources
  VOLUME IV Staff Memoranda 1. Federal Income Tax Exemption 2. Public Reporting and Accountability 3. Interviews Concerning Foundation Trusteeship 4. Proposed By-laws 5. Objectives, Scope and Method of Study 6. Proposed Michigan Foundation 7. Foundation Trustees 8. Financial Planning 9. Human Welfare and the Relative Importance of Problems and Programs 10. Location of Operating Office 11. Ford Foundation’s Donations to Charitable Institutions 12. Organizations of the General Report 13. Problems of Initial and Special Operation 14. Directory of Advisers, Conferees and Interviewees